Guide to the Max Beerbohm Collection
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
Max Beerbohm collection
1896-1945
GEN MSS 133
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
2.25
(2 boxes)
Correspondence, manuscripts of writings, and artwork by, to, or pertaining to Max Beerbohm.
Other Storage Formats: Oversize
Beerbohm, Max, Sir, 1872-1956
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Ongoing collection of documents acquired by gift and purchase from various sources.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Scope and Contents
This listing encompasses accessions of single manuscripts and small groups of manuscripts pertaining to Max Beerbohm. Materials acquired prior to January 1995 have been arranged in three series. Series I, Letters, consists of letters by Max Beerbohm and is alphabetically arranged by recipient. Series II, Writings, contains writings by Max Beerbohm and is arranged alphabetically by title. Series III, Artwork, contains drawings and sketches by Max Beerbohm and is arranged alphabetically by title of work.
Authors, English -- 19th century -- Archives; Beerbohm, Max, Sir, 1872-1956
- Letters, 1897 Oct 1; Series I
  - Letter to "Dear Sir", 1897 Oct 1 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    Scope and Contents
    1 item (1 leaf); 28 cm.
    Bequest, 1954.
  - Letter to Earl E. Fisk, 1926 Aug 14 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    1 item ( 1 leaf); 25 cm.
    Letter includes colored self-caricature
    by Beerbohm.
    Included with letter are materials by
    Earl E. Fisk intended for use in
    printing text of letter as a
    Christmas momento.
    Purchase, 1956.
  - Letters to Mrs. Thomas Hardy (Florence Dugdale Hardy), 1928 Jan 14 (Box 1, Folder 3)
    2 items
    Letters from Beerbohm and his wife,
    Florence Kahn Beerbohm, concerning the
    death of Thomas Hardy.
  - Letter [facsimile] to Edmond Kapp, [1919?] (Box 1, Folder 4)
    1 item (1 leaf); 15 cm.
    Probably refers to Kopp's exhibition
    in 1919.
  - Letters to Richard Le Gallienne, 1899-1900, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 5)
    6 items.
    Includes typewritten transcriptions of
    letters.
    Gift
  - Letter to Ada Leverson, [1896?] (Box 1, Folder 6)
    1 item (2 leaves); 15 cm.
  - Letter to Ada Leverson, 1908 Dec 1 (Box 1, Folder 7)
    1 item (3 leaves); 15 cm.
    Gift, 1954.
  - Letters to Henry Marillier, 1928 (Box 1, Folder 8)
    2 items.
    Purchase, 1974.
  - Letters to Mrs. Henry Marillier, 1928, 1939 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Letter to "Mr. Robinson", 1942 Aug 20 (Box 1, Folder 10)
    1 item (1 leaf); 18 cm.
  - Letter to "Gentlemen" [Mr. Robinson?], 1943 May 31 (Box 1, Folder 11)
    1 item (1 leaf); 23 cm.
  - Letter to Edward Fordham Spence, 1903 May 31 (Box 1, Folder 12)
    1 item (2 leaves); 18 cm.
    Includes typewritten transcription of
    letter and notes from auction catalog.
    Purchase, 1943.
  - Letter to Mrs. Tremlett of Hutchinson and Co., 1 item (4 leaves); 21 cm. or smaller (Box 1, Folder 13)
    Includes pages of instructions about photographs for Herbert Beerbohm Tree, edited by Max Beerbohm.
    Includes note explaining letter.
    Immediate Source of Acquisition
- Writings, n.d.; Series II
  - "A Ballade of My Betters," holograph, corrected, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 14)
    1 item (1 leaf); 32 cm.
    Poem.
    Included on manuscript is a caricature
    in pencil.
    Included on same page is an "Envoi"
    "Ballade of my Betters," "Envoi," and
    notes on these poems.
    Includes on verso a poem, "L.S.,"
    holograph, corrected, with caricatures
    of Lytton Strachey in pencil.
    Gift.
  - "A Clergyman," printed version, corrected, 1919 May (Box 1, Folder 15)
    1 item (3 leaves out of 26): 32 cm. x
    23 cm.; in cloth slipcase.
    Text concerning "Boswell," "Johnson,"
    and "A Clergyman."
    In The Owl, no. 1, May, 1919.
    Includes typescript list of Beerbohm's
    corrections made by Herman Liebert.
    Gift, 1994.
  - "Enoch Soames: A Memory of the Eighteen- Nineties," holograph, corrected, ca. 1919 (Box 1, Folder 16)
    1 item (24 leaves); 32 cm.
    Short story.
    Includes notes from auction catalog and
    note by Beerbohm, "For the Red Cross,
    1940 [...]"
    Bequest, [1954?]
  - Note removed from The Poets Corner, "This copy belongs to Stanley Parker [...]," holograph, 1945 Jul (Box 1, Folder 17)
    1 item ( 1 leaf); 18 cm.
    Note in unknown hand is on reverse side
    over printed illustration of Beerbohm.
    Gift, 1972.
  - "No. 2. The Pines," holograph, corrected, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 18)
    1 item (21 leaves): ill.; 33 cm.
    Essay
    Includes caricature pencil sketches
    of Algernon Swinburne, James McNeill
    Whistler and Theodore Watts-Dunton
    verso of leaves.
    Includes notes from auction catalogs
    and from an exhibition of the
    manuscript.
  - "'Savonarola' Brown," holograph, corrected, n.d. (Box 2, Folder 19)
    1 v. (24 leaves), bound in codex
    40 cm.
    Story
    Includes 5 leaves of another draft laid
    in, with typewritten transcript.
    Inscribed to John Drinkwater, May,
    1923.
  - "A Short But True Story," holograph, corrected, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 20)
    1 item (6 leaves); 33 cm.
    Short story
  - "Something Defeasible," holograph, corrected, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 21)
    1 v. (4 leaves), bound in codex
    34 cm.
    Bequest, 1954
- Artwork, 1912, 1927, n.d.; Series III
  - Caricatures, 1912, 1927, n.d. (Box 2, Folder 22-28)
    7 items: 46.5 cm. x 38.5 cm.
    Caricatures of the following:
    1. "Mr. Hilaire Belloc," pencil, ink,
    and watercolor on paper, mounted on
    board, signed.
    2. "Mr. Belloc on British Literature,"
    ink, watercolor and newspaper
    clipping on paper, mounted in board,
    signed and dated: October, 1927.
    Includes caricature of Lytton Strachey.
    3. "Clyde Fitch," ink and watercolor
    on paper, mounted on board, signed.
    4. "Mr. G. K. Chesterton giving the
    world a kiss," pencil on paper,
    mounted on board, signed.
    5. "La France de Demain," ink and
    watercolor on paper, mounted on board,
    signed.
    6. "Signor Caruso, cynosure--," ink,
    pencil and watercolor on paper, mounted
    on board, signed and dated, 1912.
    7. "Such Good 'Copy'," pencil and
  - "Dante Gabriel Rosetti, in his back garden," tracing made by Kate Kaufman and sent to Beerbohm for annotations, photostat. (Box 2, Folder 29)
    1 item (1 leaf); 27 cm.
    Removed from copy (discarded) of
    Beerbohm's The Poet's Corner.
  - Frontispiece to "Three Plays for Puritans" [by G.B. Shaw], n.d. (Box 2, Folder 30)
    Pen and ink on paper, signed "Max",
    mounted on board.
    Gift, 1956.
  - "Mr. H. G. Wells and his Patent Mechanical New Republic; and the Spirit of Pure Reason Crowning him President (View of Presidential Palace in background)" (Box 2, Folder 31)
    Pen and ink on paper, mounted on board,
    signed "Max".
  - "Sir Philip Sassoon in the House of Commons", 1913 (Box 2, Folder 32)
    1 item (1 leaf); 30 cm.
    Pen and ink on paper, signed "Max,
    1913", framed.